Hosting ASP.NET Core App in a Docker container.
It's time we are all waiting for to host an ASP.NET Core App in a Docker container.
This is an important topic, so make sure you concentrate on what I am doing.
Also, you should do this side-by-side on your PC with me.
This way, you will learn it more quickly, open Visual Studio.
Click create a new project.
Next, select deed ASP.NET Core Web App model view controller template.
Name the project something like First Docker App.
Then choose the location on your PC where you want to save this app.
There is a checkbox that says place solution and project in the same directory.
You need to check this option.
This is very necessary because Docker needs to find the .NET App files on the saved location.
If you uncheck this option, then Docker will not be able to find the .NET App files
and it will fail to create a container.
Click next.
Here, select the framework.
I am selecting latest .NET 10.
Here, see the checkbox saying enable container support.
You can check this option if you want to host the app from the Docker container from the beginning.
You can also enable container support, which is Docker after the app is created.
I will keep this option unchecked because I want to show how you can add Docker container support to apps
that are already functioning.
This will help you to learn Docker in greater depth.
Now click the create button.
This will create the .NET App.
The app is created.
Let us run it.
It is just a basic app containing only two pages, home and privacy.
Close the browser and the console window.
In the Docker desktop, you can see I have no images and no containers right now.
Now, on Visual Studio, let's add Docker container support.
So, right click on the project name, select add menu option.
Then you will see the option saying container support.
Click on this option, which will add Docker container support to the .NET App.
In new window opens where you can select container options.
On the container OS, select line X container build type.
Let it remain Docker file.
Container image distro.
You can select the line X version like Ubuntu, Debian, Alpine, etc.
Let it also remain default.
For container build context, let it remain as it is.
Next, click the ok button.
Visual Studio has added Docker support to the app.
And Docker file is created for this app.
Notice on the left bottom corner.
Visual Studio is now performing some task.
It is actually creating the Docker image of this app.
And also creating a line X based Docker container that will host this app's image.
Now, the task is completed.
If you open Docker desktop, you will now see two images created on the Docker server.
The first one is tsp.net.
10.0 image which is downloaded from Azure container registry.
This registry is also known as Microsoft container registry.
Shortform MCR.
Second image is the apps image which Docker has created.
The image name is kept same as the apps name.
Now go to the container section where you will find a new container.
Having the name first Docker app.
This container is actually hosting our.net apps image.
Visual Studio has lots of inbuilt Docker features.
And I should explain them to you now.
On the output window select container tools.
Here you will see the different task which Docker has performed.
Like pulling.net 10.0 image from MCR starting containers, creating image layers and setting the whole image of the.net app.
Finally, there is a Docker run command which is creating the Docker container for running the.net apps image.
On visual studio me know you will also find a new container Docker file option which will enable you to start the Docker container from visual studio itself.
Click this option to run the app.
Visual Studio opens the container window showing the container and image of this app.
Congratulations you can now see the app is hosted from a Docker container and it's working correctly.
Also, you will see environment variables.
Ports, volumes, logs, etc.
Actually, it has switched all the details from Docker desktop.
Now open Docker desktop then click the container name.
You will see the logs, files, stats and other informations which you already saw on visual studio.
On the exe tab you can run line X commands like ls which list all the files and folders inside the container.
Also find the ports of the host machine and container ports.
These ports are actually listed on the Docker file.